<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Sathyam Vellal]]></title>
  <link href="https://sathyam.me/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://sathyam.me/"/>
  <updated>2018-11-13T23:40:17+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://sathyam.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[sathyam@vellals.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bohemian Rhapsody]]></title>
    <link href="https://sathyam.me/blog/10/"/>
    <updated>2018-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://sathyam.me/blog/bohemian-rhapsody</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>⭐⭐⭐⭐⭐</p>

<p>I’m a kid from the 90s and never really experienced the musical sensations of the 80s. During my primary and high schooling years, friends sung “We Will Rock You”, and I went along as well. Somewhere later, I came across Bohemian Rhapsody, and loved it, even though I couldn’t make much sense of the lyrics.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Years later, however, when I became more aware of my closeted self, I realised the meaning of Bohemian Rhapsody - it was a song about a boy coming out to his mother. It freaked me out, and I just never listened to it again. My friends used to enjoy playing and singing it with tonal accuracy, and I would just act like nothing was going on.</p>

<p>The movie Bohemian Rhapsody gives a historical look into the rise of Queen, the song ‘Bohemian Rhapsody’, culminating with the Love Aid concert in 1985. While it doesn’t do a heartfelt job of Freddie Mercury dealing with his sexuality, in my opinion, we do see Freddie Mercury dealing with it. Of course, movies cannot show all aspects in great depth, and I can understand.</p>

<p>What it definitely did well, was transport me to the 80s, to experience the magnificence of Queen, Rami Malek is absolutely incredible as Freddie Mercury. Perfect casting, and acting. Comparing with the actual video of the Live Aid, his portrayal of Freddie Mercury is spot on! I’m just so grateful to have <em>experienced</em> Queen, even if virtually.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
